Network File System, NFS, is the strategic file sharing protocol for the ZOS platform.
The DFSMS MVS MVS server, or NFSS, feature implements the NFS protocols.
NFSS enables the host processor to act as a file server to authorize NFS clients and a TCP IP
network. NFSS allows remote access to data on the ZOS host from workstations, personal computers,
or any system in the network that is using NFS client software. A client system can be
Windows or any Unix or Linux system with the NFS client software and ZOS. And the NFS server allows
access to ZOS data sets and HFS files on the ZOS host as if they were local files on the client
system. A workstation user can access the ZOS file system by using the NVS logging command to log
into ZOS. A ZOS user ID, password and authorization to access requested files is needed.
The mount command is used to create a temporary link between specific ZOS data sets and an empty
Unix directory or a dummy PC drive. A ZOS high level qualifier is used in the mount command
to specify which ZOS data sets to mount at a mount point. The ZOS data sets beginning with
the specified high level qualifier appear as files under the mount point. If the specified
data sets include partition data sets, a second level of hierarchy is shown. The NFS support
for ZOS Unix provides transparent access to HFS file systems mounted by an NFS client.
The NFS client user is not restricted to the ZOS naming conventions for HFS data access.
Path names and file names can contain special characters and can be mixed cased, just go wild.
An NFS client user can mount a part of the ZOS Unix HFS on their local file system and thereafter
create, delete, rewrite and otherwise treat that part of the ZOS Unix file system
as an extension to their local workstation file system.
Okay, so let's transition into file security. In ZOS Unix, each user has a user ID, a UID and
a group ID, a GID. When a user creates a directory or a file, it's automatically associated with the
user's GID and the GID is set to the GID of the parent directory. A user's UID and GID can be
defined in RACF or an equivalent security product. The system verifies that the user or
a program has access to a file by comparing the UID and GID in RACF with the definitions
in the hierarchical file system. There are three classes of users, there's owner, the user's UID
must match the UID for the file, there's group, a member of any group whose GID matches the GID of
the file, and other which is anyone else. Access to files on directories is controlled
by permission bits. Each file gets its permission bits set when it's created. The permission bits
can be changed by the chmod command. Those are read notated by R, write notated by W and execute
notated by X. The diagram here shows a conceptual overview of how file security is controlled.
A user with UID 103 and GID 42 wants to open file slash user slash lib slash lib dot a.
The system checks with RACF if UID 103 and GID 42 are valid and if they are valid what authority
they have to access the file lib dot a. User GID 103 is not the owner of this file but belongs to
the same group the file is associated with. The group permission is RWX which means this user will
have rewrite and execute access to the file. Now as this chart shows the permission bits have
different meanings when related to files and directories. If you want to put a new file in a
directory you need both search and write access to the directory. The system needs to search the
directory to determine if the entry is already there. As you create files on directories default
permission bits are defined. These differ depending on the method used to create the entity.
The zosunix file system can be accessed by using a bunch of methods. TCOE has commands for browsing
and editing HFS files, copying data between HFS files and zos datasets, mounting file
systems and invoking the zosunix shell. There's also a command called ishell which provides an
ISPF menu driven interface to the file system. GCL provides keywords which support the specification
of HFS path names. REX has a set of zosunix extensions, syscall commands to access zosunix
callable services. zosunix shell is the Unix interface to the file system. It contains
commands and utilities to access HFS files. zosunix supports many C functions to access HFS files and
finally shell script which are similar to REX execs where shell commands and utilities can be stored
in a text file which can be executed. There are TSOE commands which support the hierarchical files.
So for example mkdir creates a new directory and mknod creates a character special file.
oedit creates or edits a file using the ISPF editor and obrowse browses a file using ISPF
and ishell or ish invokes the zosispf shell PAL interface.
File copy between zos datasets and HFS files can be useful if you need to send and
receive files between zos systems for DFSMS backup and restore of HFS files or to copy HFS files to
tapes. oget copies an HFS file into a zos sequential file or to a pds pdsc member.
copage conversion can also be specified. oget x does the same thing for an HFS directory.
oput copies a zos sequential file or a pdsc member into an HFS file and oput x copies all members of
a pds or pdsc into an HFS directory. And ocopy copies data in either direction between a zos
dataset and an HFS file using dd names. The cp and mv Unix commands have support for zos datasets.
To specify a zos dataset name proceed the name with double forward slashes.
To cp or mv to a pds or a pdse the dataset must be allocated before the copy or move.
The same is true for pax and tar for creating portable archives or extracting files from the
archive. Don't forget those double forward slashes for zos dataset names. And speaking of which let's
quickly recap the difference in file identification. In zos a dataset is identified by a dataset name.
If the dataset is a pds or a pdse the file has a member name. The characteristics of the
dataset are kept in catalogs or the VTOC, the volume table of contents. Executable modules
can have multiple names for an alias. In the hierarchical file systems files are identified
by path names which consists of directory names and file name. Files can have multiple names
created by symbolic links and hardlinks. There's no concept of a defined record format or block
size but despite these differences as you can see there's some great support between zos datasets
and zos Unix files. And that wraps up the module. Like I said at the beginning there
was a lot to cover here but this gives us a great grounding for the rest of the class.